Guide to the Harold B. Barth Scrapbook Collection, 1889-1974 CTC.1967.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Harold B. Barth Scrapbook Collection
Bulk, 1905-1967
1889-1974
CTC.1967.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
13.0 linear feet (29 mss. boxes)
The Barth Scrapbook Collection documents the performing arts in Pittsburgh and East Liverpool, Ohio. There are 41 volumes of programs, clippings, and other documents that date from the late nineteenth century through the 1960's.
Barth, Harold B. (Harold Bradshaw), 1884-1974
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harold B. Barth in 1967.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
Harold Barth organized his scrapbooks in volumes according to subject, i.e. drama, music, motion pictures, etc. Twenty-one volumes contain programs accompanied by related clippings (although scrapbooks for motion pictures are primarily clippings), presumably for those performances that Barth attended between 1905-1967. All of these programs are mounted in loose-leaf albums. For clippings of interest from magazine and newspapers, Barth used bound ledger books (scrapbooks 22-34, 40) and composition books (scrapbooks 35-39). The final volume is a loose-leaf notebook presented to the Curtis Collection by Eva Wasbutsky, Barth's secretary, after his death. Barth was in interested in all of the performing arts, but mostly in theatre and film. His primary collection focus was on Shakespeare; the final volumes consist of Shakespearean productions on stage, film, radio, and televsion.
The scrapbooks have been organized into categories according to form and content, arranged, as much as possible, in chronological order, and assigned numbers. Loose souvenir programs, pamphlets, and clippings were removed and integrated into other areas in the Curtis Collection.
Biography
Harold Bradshaw Barth, 1884-1974, was the grandson of one of East Liverpool's earliest settlers. Barth was also a life-long resident of the community except for a brief period as a young man. He was a graduate of the Byron King School of Oratory, a school of dramatic art in Pittsburgh. He later studied under the noted actor, Frederick Warde, and for a few years performed with the Ben Greet Troupe, Shakespearean Players. This early interest in the stage influenced his collecting interests which yielded an enthusiastic accumulation of theatrical memorabilia spanning more than 60 years.
Barth returned to East Liverpool, Ohio, after the death of his father in 1907 to begin a long and active career in civic life, serving in voluntary roles within municipal, county, state, and federal agencies. He was one of the organizers of East Liverpool's Rotary Club and served as the organization's Secretary for 50 years. He also had a long association with the East Liverpool Chamber of Commerce.
Local history was of particular interest to him. His two-volume history of Columbiana County was published in 1926. He was a member of the East Liverpool Historical Society, first elected to its Board of Trustees in 1920. He later served as Secretary and later, President. For many years until his death, he served as the Curator of the Society's Museum and developed a notable collection of pottery and local artifacts.
Previous Citation
Harold B. Barth Scrapbook Collection, 1889-1974, CTC.1967.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Performing arts -- Ohio -- East Liverpool; Performing arts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616 -- Stage history -- Ohio -- East Liverpool; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616 -- Stage history -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Theater -- Ohio -- East Liverpool; Theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh
- Drama - Oversized scrapbook, 1905-1925; 40 x 54 cm. (Box 1, Volume 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  This volume contains programs, newspaper reviews, and advertisements. The majority of the programs are from performances held in East Liverpool and Pittsburgh. Some major Pittsburgh theatres represented in this volume are Alvin, Avenue, Belasco, Dusquesne, Gayety, Nixon, and the Pitt Theatre. The major theatres from East Liverpool include the American and Ceramic Theatres. The volume also includes a few Ohio Chautauqua programs.
  This volume continues with volumes 6-8.
- Musicals - Oversized scrapbook, 1905-1964; 40 x 54 cm. (Box 2, Volume 2)
  This volume contains programs of musical comedies and revues, newspaper clippings and reviews, and advertisements. Major theatres represented in this volume are the Academy, Alvin, Avenue, Belasco, Duquesne, Gayety, Pitt, and Victoria in Pittsburgh. Major theatres in East Liverpool included are the American, Ceramic, and McKinley Theatres.
- Vaudeville - Oversized scrapbook, 1905-1959; 40 x 54 cm. (Box 3, Volume 3)
  This volume includes programs, newspaper reviews, and advertisements. The programs are from performances at East Liverpool and Pittsburgh Theatres. The East Liverpool programs are chiefly from the American, Ceramic, and McKinley Theatres. The majority of the Pittsburgh programs are from the Grand Opera House. There are a few other tri-state programs that are included in this volume, including Rock Springs Theatre in Chester, WV.
- Music - Oversized scrapbook, 1905-1927; 40 x 54 cm. (Box 4, Volume 4)
  This volume contains programs and newspaper clippings. These programs are from concerts, expositions, operas, and recitals. The majority of these performances are from East Liverpool and Pittsburgh. Some major Pittsburgh locations include the Carnegie Music Hall, Luna Park, the Pittsburgh Exposition, and the Syria Mosque.
- Motion pictures - Oversized scrapbook, 1912-1929?; 40 x 54 cm. (Box 5, Volume 5)
  This volume includes newspaper advertisements, programs, and some reviews. The majority of this volume is from East Liverpool theatres, with some material from Pittsburgh.
- Drama, 1926-1933; 24 x 36 cm. (Box 6, Volume 6)
  This volume is a continuation from volume 1 which includes programs, newspaper reviews, and advertisements. The programs are chiefly from Pittsburgh, with some others from Cleveland, East Liverpool, Montreal, New York City, Washington, D.C., and Youngstown.
- Drama, 1934-1966; 24 x 36 cm. (Box 7, Volume 7)
  This volume is a continuation from Volumes 1 and 6, which includes programs, newspapers reviews, and advertisements. Prior to 1949, this volume includes performances from theatres in Pittsburgh, Ohio, New York City, and Washington, D.C. After 1949, this volume includes radio and TV dramas.
- Shakespearean drama, 1907-1966; 26 x 34 cm. (Box 8, Volume 8)
  This volume is a continuation from Volume 1, which includes programs, newspaper reviews, and advertisements. The programs are predominantly from the Nixon Theatre, Pittsburgh and the Pittsburgh Playhouse, along with some other Pittsburgh theatres. The advertisements and reviews are from New York, Ohio, and Pittsburgh newspapers. This volume also includes newspaper clippings on radio and film productions.
- Vaudeville, 1926-1951; 24 x 36 cm. (Box 9, Volume 9)
  This volume is a supplement to Volume 3, which includes programs, newspaper reviews, and advertisements from performances in East Liverpool and Pittsburgh. Programs from Boston and Colorado Springs as well as a souvenire program from Balieff's Chauve-Souris are included in this volume.
- Music, 1927-1941; 24 x 36 cm. (Box 10, Volume 10)
  This volume is a supplement to Volume 4, which includes programs and newspaper clippings. This volume contains programs and newspaper clippings of concerts, operas, and recitals. The majority of these performances are from Pittsburgh. This volume also includes newspaper clippings of radio music programs from 1936-1941.
- Motion pictures, 1929-1950; 24 x 36 cm. (Box 11, Volumes 11-13)
  Volumes 11-13 are a continuation from Volume 5, which includes advertisements, programs, and reviews. These volumes largely include advertisements of movies in East Liverpool. These volumes also include the announcement of the opening of the Avenue Cinema, a Pittsburgh theatre devoted to foreign and domestic art films, along with some programs from the Avenue Cinema. Volume 13 contains a souvenir program from The Red Shoes.
- Motion pictures, 1950-1957; 37 x 25 cm. (Box 12, Volumes 14-16)
  These volumes are a continuation from Volumes 11-13, with the addition of advertisements for Pittsburgh movie houses, such as the Warner Theatre and The Fulton. These volumes also include reviews from the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette in Pittsburgh, The Plain Dealer in Cleveland, and The New York Times in New York.
- Motion pictures, 1957-1960; 26 x 34 cm. (Box 13, Volume 17)
  This volume is a continuation of Volumes 14-16. Volume 17 contains only newspaper clippings.
- Motion pictures, 1960-1963; 33 x 29 cm. (Box 14, Volume 18)
  This volume is a continuation of Volumes 14-16. Volume 18 contains a few programs from various performances.
- Magic and dance, 1915-1966; 26 x 24 cm. (Box 15, Volume 19)
  This volume contains programs primarily from dance performances. Volume 19 also includes newspaper advertisements and reviews from magic shows, ballet and folk dance performances, and Chautauquas held in New York, Ohio, and Pittsburgh. This volume also includes a few pertinent film and television newspaper clippings.
- Minstrels and marionettes, 1907-1939; 26 x 34 cm. (Box 16, Volume 20)
  This volume chiefly contains programs for minstrel shows at the Ceramic in East Liverpool. There are only two marionette programs included in this volume; both of which are for Tony Sarg’s Marionettes at the Great Lakes Exposition, 1937.
- Festivals, Fairs, Carnivals, and Circus, 1905-1967; 26 x 34 cm. (Box 17, Volume 21)
  This volume contains programs, flyers, and newspaper advertisements for various festivals, fairs, carnivals, circuses, expositions, poultry and dog shows, parades, rodeos, horse races, dedications, memorials, exhibitions, museums, cattle auctions, flower shows, aeronautical expositions, air shows, horse shows, and races. These events were held in Ohio and Pittsburgh. Also included in this volume is a program from the 1930 Army Tournament held in Chicago, IL. Volume 21 contains loose clippings that have been transferred to 8 folders and are boxed with the scrapbook.
- Shakespeare stage and film productions, 1906-1940; 30 x 18 cm. (Box 18, Volume 22)
  This volume contains miscellaneous magazine and newspaper clippings and many photographs from Theatre Magazine.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre, 1904-1925; 30 x 18 cm. (Box 19, Volume 23)
  This volume contains miscellaneous clippings and several profiles of performers from Theatre Magazine, some New York Times articles.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre and film, 1907-1922; 30 x 18 cm. (Box 20, Volume 24)
  This volume contains miscellaneous clippings from New York, Ohio, and Pittsburgh.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre and vaudeville and film, 1910-1923; 30 x 18 cm. (Box 21, Volume 25)
  This volume contains clippings, primarily from Ohio and Pittsburgh newspapers and The New York Times, focusing on Shakespeare and Japanese theatre. It also includes several articles about theatre censorship and the fervor caused by an attempt to perform Playboy of the Western World in Philadelphia and Pittsburgh.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre and film, 1925-1930; x30 x 18 cm. (Box 22, Volume 26)
  This volume contains clippings from miscellaneous newspaper and magazine sources, including The New York Times, Literary Digest, American Mercury, Collier’s, Plain Talk, Theatre Magazine, and Elks Magazine.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre, 1925-1933; 30 x 18 cm. (Box 23, Volume 27)
  This volume contains clippings from The New York Times, Theatre Magazine, Collier’s, American Mercury, and various Pittsburgh and Cleveland newspapers. Clippings includes articles on opera, film, and stuttering.
- Miscellany, 1933-1935; 30 x 18 cm. (Volume 28)
  This volume contains clippings of articles including theatre, magic, puppets, acrobats, and additional articles on speech disorders. Sources for these articles include Esquire and Saturday Evening Post.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre, 1911-1912, 1935-1936; 30 x 18 cm. (Box 24, Volume 29)
  This volume contains clippings from major sources including The New York Times, Plain Dealer, Esquire, Collier’s, and Saturday Evening Post. The volume also includes installments of William A. Brady’s autobiography from the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre, 1936-1938; 30 x 18 cm. (Volume 30)
  This volume contains clippings from miscellaneous sources, primarily newspapers. Included are several articles about the 1937 controversy over closing New York City burlesque. This volume also includes clippings on stuttering.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre, 1939-1943; 30 x 18 cm. (Box 25, Volume 31)
  This volume contains clippings from miscellaneous sources, many from Plain Dealer. Included are the Statevepost installments on Orson Welles, a newspaper piece on road shows by Abe Laufe, and clippings on speech disorders.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly theatre, 1911-1912, 1935-1948; 30 x 18 cm. (Volume 32)
  This volume contains newspaper and magazine clippings, chiefly from The New York Times and Plain Dealer on performing arts and speech disorders. Also included are typed quotations from various books.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly Shakespeare, 1889, 1908, 1943-1949; 30 x 18 cm. (Box 26, Volume 33)
  This volume contains miscellaneous performing arts clippings which primarily focus on Shakespeare. Also included are early clippings are from Munsey’s Magazine.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly Shakespeare, 1903, 1914, 1950-1952; 30 x 18 cm. (Volume 34)
  This volume contains miscellaneous performing arts clippings, chiefly on Shakespeare. Also included are several articles on the film, The Miracle.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly Shakespeare, 1893-1994, 1951-1954; 25 x 19 cm. (Box 27, Volume 35)
  This volume contains miscellaneous performing arts clippings, chiefly on Shakespeare. Also included are early clippings from Munsey’s Magazine and several pieces on Eugene O’Neill.
- Miscellaneous but chiefly Shakespeare, 1954-1966; 25 x 19 cm. (Box 28, Volume 36-39)
  These volumes contain miscellaneous performing arts clippings. Volume 36 includes articles on burlesque. Volume 37 includes articles on the circus, Eugene O’Neill, a few films, and stuttering. Volume 38 includes a few articles on speech, radio, and TV.
- Magic, 1935-1953; 30 x 18 cm. (Volume 40)
  This volume contains clippings on magic and the occult from miscellaneous newspapers and magazines. Also included is the Plain Dealer series on Harry Blackstone's tricks photographed.
- Shakespeare and miscellany, 1966-1974; 29 x 24 cm. (Volume 41)
  This volume includes xeroxed copies from several books, including Ellen Terry’s notes on Lady Macbeth. Also included are a few newspaper clippings and typed notes.